Guide to the Herman Rosenstein Papers ALBA.129
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Herman Rosenstein Papers
1936-1993
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Rosenstein, Herman, 1915-
ALBA.129
3 Linear Feet in 4 boxes
Herman Rosenstein (1915-c.2000) fought with the International Brigades in Spain from June 1937 until the winter of 1938, using the nom de guerre Herman "Gabby" Klein. A first-aid worker during World War II, Rosenstein remained active in community and international politics throughout his life. This collection consists of Rosenstein's letters, military documents and memorabilia from Spain, as well as articles, correspondence and other material from Rosenstein's life after the Spanish Civil War.
Provenance
The Herman Rosenstein Papers came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University. An additional donation of material was made by the Rosenstein family in July 2006. A third donation was received from Ada Hollie and Paul Rosenstein via ALBA in March 2011.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Herman Rosenstein was born in 1915, son of a garment worker and the youngest of five children. During the Depression Rosenstein worked as a bookkeeper for the William Morris Agency in New York City. He came into political awareness at a time when the threat of Nazism was making itself felt even in his Jewish neighborhood in the borough of Queens, New York. But when Rosenstein declared that he was going to Spain to join the antifascists in the International Brigades, his mother tried to prevent him from going by taking away his passport. Rosenstein soon procured another one, using his mother's maiden name, Klein, and sailed for Spain in June 1937. Going by the name Herman "Gabby" Klein throughout his time in Spain, Rosenstein fought at first with the Canadian Mackenzie-Papineau Battalion, and later transferred to the Lincoln-Washington Battalion. He saw heavy action, distinguishing himself in battle, and was promoted to sergeant. Rosenstein remained in Spain until the International Brigades were evacuated from the country in the winter of 1938.
During World War II Rosenstein was a first-aid worker, seeing action in the Pacific and in Europe. After the war, he worked as an auto mechanic, an electrician, a warrant officer, and later on the Housing Commission in Santa Monica, California. Rosenstein was a community activist and member of the California Democratic Council. He participated in Vietnam anti-war marches and supported numerous other political causes. He remained involved with the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB) throughout his life, in 1986 traveling to Nicaragua with other veterans in support of the new Sandinista government. Rosenstein married his wife, Mildred, in 1941. They had a son, Paul, who became mayor of Santa Monica; and a daughter, Frances.
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Spanish Civil War Files, 1936-1939, consists of Rosenstein's letters to his sister, Gertrude (signed with his family nickname, Hymie); memorabilia, including Spanish and German banknotes with handwritten notations indicating that they were taken from prisoners in Belchite, Teruel, and Fatarella; and a copy of the Lincoln Brigade newsletter "Our Fight," with a piece on Rosenstein's heroic actions in battle.
Series II: Correspondence, Clippings and Subject Files, 1941-1993, consists of articles about Rosenstein and other veterans, including reports of their involvement with the Nicaraguan revolution in the 1980s. Also included are certificates of recognition and citations for Rosenstein's community activities; correspondence; and membership books and other VALB material.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically within each series.
Organized into two series:
Missing Title
Series I: Spanish Civil War, 1936-1939.
Series II: Correspondence, Clippings and Subject Files, 1941-1993.
Series III: Unprocessed Material
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Herman Rosenstein interview, in Manny Harriman Video Oral History Collection, ALBA Video 048.
Correspondence.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Memorabilia.; Articles.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV -- biography.; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Rosenstein, Herman, 1915-; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV
- Series I: Spanish Civil War Files, 1936-1939.
  - Correspondence: Rosenstein, Herman to Gertrude Rosenstein, Jul 1937-Sep 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, Dec 1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Memorabilia: Tickets, stamps, money, dues book, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Military documents, undated, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Our Fight(newsletter): Article on Rosenstein, Aug 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II: Correspondence, Clippings and Subject Files, 1941-1993.
  - Awards and citations: Rosenstein, Herman, Mar 1984-Jul 1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings: Re: HR, Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Activities in California, 1984-1987, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: HR, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: HR, Sep 1941-Jan 1942, Dec 1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Dolores Ibárruri and Herman and Mildred Rosenstein, 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Re: Spain, 1979, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Course on the Spanish Civil War Taught by HR: Description, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - German Commemoration of Thirtieth Anniversary of Spanish Civil War, Berlin, DDR, Jul 1966 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Maps and Article: Re: Battles at the Ebro, Madrid, Teruel, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Poems: Re: VALB by Rewi Alley, Flor Cernuda, Jimmy Jump, 1974, 1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Proclamation of VALB Day, Santa Monica, California, Mar 1, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Spanish Government Documents, 1987, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - VALB: California Events, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - VALB: Los Angeles Post, Correspondence and Miscellaneous Documents, 1967-1983 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - VALB: National Office Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Series III: Unprocessed Materials
  - Unprocessed Materials (Box 2, Box 3)
  - Scarves and Picasso Flag, undated (Box 4)